For today we're doing בכורות ו עמוד ב, Bechorot vav amud bais,
we start with the very bottom of ה עמוד ב. hay amud
bais. We are figuring out the issue first of all about things
that are born to donkeys that don't look like donkeys and sheep
that don't look like sheep, etc. And on a little bit of
a digression, one of the ways we learned it out was from
the בכור שור בכור עז, Bechor Shor Bechor Ez, and one of
the ways the person who does not learn it out, the תנא
Tanna who does not learn it out from that, says that it's
coming to tell you why all those three categories you have to
put the fats on the מזבח, mizbeach, on the altar. So now
the גמרא Gemara is saying,
let's see,
one minute, I'm sorry, הלכך רבי יוסי הגלילי, Hilkach Rebbe Yose HaGlili,
I'm sorry, I lost my place, one minute. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, two lines before the lines
get wide. It says the following, middle of the line: חדה מחדא
לא אתיא. Chada mi-chada lo atya. So you can't learn one from
the other. Couldn't just say by the ox or by the sheep
or by the goat this idea of the fats. תיתי חדה מתרתי.
Teisi chada mi-tarti. Learn one from two. Why did it say by
two of them and I could have figured out the third? So
בהאי לא לכתוב. Behai lo lichtov. Which one should it not write
it by? לא לכתוב רחמנא בשור, Lo lichtov Rachmana b'shor, don't write
by the ox, ותיתי מהנך, v'teisi meihanoch, learn it out from the
fact that the fats of the sheep and the goat go on
the altar by a בכור. Bechor. No, מה הנך שכן ריבו בפסחים.
Ma hanoch shekein ribu b'pesachim. Those have a special status that they're
both brought as a קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, so maybe they have
a special status that their fat goes on the altar. Of course
it's quite funny because of course for all קרבנות, korbanot, not only
that, but for all קרבנות korbanot their fat go on the altar,
but the fact תורה Torah pointed it out by בכור Bechor and
therefore it's saying that for some reason if a בכור Bechor was
not like other קרבנות, korbanot, I couldn't have just figured it out
from those two because those two have a special status. Okay. לא
לכתוב בכשב, Lo lichtov b'chesev, don't write it by the sheep, ותיתי
מהנך, v'teisi meihanoch, learn it out from the ox and from the
calf and from the goat. No, מה הנך שכן ריבו בעבודה זרה
בציבור. Ma hanoch shekein ribu b'avodah zarah b'tzibur.
Both the cow and goat, or ox and goat, are special קרבנות
korbanot for עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, which the sheep is not, so
maybe that gives them some special status. לא לכתוב רחמנא בעז, Lo
lichtov Rachmana b'eiz, don't write it by a goat, ותיתי מהנך, v'teisi
meihanoch, and learn it out from the sheep and the cow. No,
מה הנך שכן יש בהן צד ריבוי את המזבח. Ma hanoch shekein
yesh bahen tzad ribuy et hamizbeach. Both sheep and cow have something
special goes on the altar. The sheep has the fat tail, the
cow has the extra wine because it's a larger animal, gets a
larger amount of wine, so therefore I would not have applied it
to goat. הלכך צריכי, Hilkach tzrichi, therefore it had to say by
all of them. Okay fine. רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rebbe Yose HaGlili, what
would רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbe Yose HaGlili say back? How does he
use the fact it says בכור שור בכור כשב בכור עז Bechor
Shor Bechor Chesev Bechor Eiz to learn out the idea that the
mother and the child have to look the same? Doesn't he need
to learn it out this idea that you put all of the
fat on the altar? No, אם כן לכתוב קרא אך בכור שור
כשב ועז. Im kein lichtov kra ach bechor shor chesev va-eiz.
So that's why it had to write all three animals, ox, sheep,
and goat, but why did it have to write the word בכור
Bechor by each of them? בכור בכור למה לי? Bechor Bechor lama
li? Why did it say בכור שור בכור כשב בכור עז? Bechor
Shor Bechor Chesev Bechor Eiz? אלא לאו שמע מינה כשהוא שור בכורו
שור, Ela lav shma mina, k’shehu shor bechoro shor,
to tell you this idea that both the child and mother have
to look the same. Okay. רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rebbe Yose HaGlili, האי
פטר חמור פטר חמור, hai Peter Chamor Peter Chamor, now that we've
explained what the rabbis do with בכור שור בכור כשב, Bechor Shor
Bechor Chesev, they learn out from the idea it says פטר חמור
פטר חמור Peter Chamor Peter Chamor twice this principle of mother and
child and apply it to the kosher animals. רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbe
Yose HaGlili starts from the kosher animals, applies it to the donkey.
So now we have to ask what he does with this דרשה
drasha by the donkeys. האי פטר חמור פטר חמור מאי עביד ליה?
Hai Peter Chamor Peter Chamor mai avid leih? What does he do
with this idea that twice it says the firstborn of the donkey,
if he doesn't need it to say the mother and child have
to look the same?
I shouldn't say mother and child have to look the same, it's
not like the שני שעירים shnei se'irim on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
I mean that both the mother and the child have to look
of the right species. Anyway, מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, mibaya leih l'cheidei tanya,
like we taught in the ברייתא. Baraita. רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר, Rebbe
Yose HaGlili omer, מתוך שנאמר אך פדה תפדה את בכור האדם ואת
בכור הבהמה הטמאה תפדה. Mitoch shene'emar ach padoh tifdeh es bechor ha-adam
v'es bechor ha-beheimah ha-tmeiah tifdeh. You should redeem the firstborn of humans
and the firstborn donkey. שומע אני אפילו פטרי סוסים וגמלים. Shomeia ani
afilu pitrei susim v’gamalim.
Now actually he, now we're actually going to turn to a
real interesting question about פשט pshat of the פסוקים, psukim, which is,
you know the פסוקים psukim say redeem the firstborn of your non-kosher
animals in a very generic sense. And then a פסוק pasuk says
the firstborn donkey redeem with a sheep. So which is it? Is
it all my non-kosher animals or just the firstborn donkey? And there's
actually a way to resolve that, because you could say all the
firstborn animals, even of the non-kosher animals, I have to redeem, but
the donkey I'm entitled to redeem with a sheep. Right? What we
do is we take the פסוק pasuk that says redeem the firstborn
of non-kosher animals and we narrow it to only talk about the
donkey. And that's what רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbe Yose HaGlili is going
to ask. How do you know to do that? Maybe we should
take the verse literally. So let's take a look. It says בכור
בהמה הטמאה תפדה, bechor behemah hatmeiah tifdeh, redeem the firstborn of the
non-kosher animal. שומע אני אפילו פטרי סוסים וגמלים, Shomeia ani afilu pitrei
susim v’gamalim, maybe even the firstborn of the horses and of the
camels. תלמוד לומר פטר חמור. Talmud lomar Peter Chamor. It says no,
because another verse says ופטר חמור תפדה בשה, u’peter chamor tifdeh baseh,
the firstborn donkey. פטר חמור אמרתי לך
ולא פטרי סוסים וגמלים, Peter chamor amarti lecha v’lo pitrei susim v’gamalim,
only the firstborn donkey. ועדיין אני אומר, v'adayin ani omer, I might
still say, פטרי חמור בשה, pitrei chamor baseh,
firstborn donkeys have the special rule that you redeem it with a
sheep. By the way, with We're going to say this later but
just so that you understand, you don't have to redeem with a
sheep, the גמרא, Gemara, the משנה Mishnah is going to make clear
you can redeem firstborn donkeys with their value, but you're allowed to
redeem it with a sheep and the sheep can even be less
than its value. Okay, so just understand the idea of redeeming with
a sheep, doesn't have to be a sheep, you're allowed to redeem
it with a sheep. Anyway, maybe I would have said that firstborn
donkeys have this rule of redeeming with a sheep, פטרי סוסים וגמלים
בכל
דבר, pitrei susim ugemalim bechol davar, the horses and the camels cannot
be a sheep but would be with something else, so maybe it's
only the sheep aspect which is limited to donkeys but the מצוה
mitzvah of redeeming applies to all firstborn animals even non-kosher ones. Top
of ו עמוד א, vav amud aleph, so תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar,
the verse teaches פטר חמור פטר חמור שתי פעמים, peter chamor peter
chamor shtei pe'amim, it says twice פטר חמור. peter chamor. פטרי חמורים
אמרתי לך ולא פטרי סוסים וגמלים, pitrei chamorim amarti lecha velo pitrei
susim ugemalim,
so once to tell you it's just limited to sheep but the
other to tell you really this whole מצוה mitzvah of redeeming by
non-kosher animals is only by donkeys.
Why say בכורים bechorim at the beginning then?
That is a good question. Yeah, the גמרא Gemara never goes back
to answer. Okay, but that is a good question. Okay, now we
have פריך רב אחאי. parich Rav Achai. Now we had this yesterday
as well, remember הוי בי רב אחאי, havi be-Rav Achai, פריך רב
אחאי. parich Rav Achai. As I mentioned yesterday, תוספות Tosafot thinks that
this is רב אחאי גאון Rav Achai Gaon of the שאילתות, She'iltot,
regardless of exactly which רב אחאי Rav Achai it is, it clearly
both by the language and the nature of the questions always very
much is like a side-type of a question and basically תוספות Tosafot
feels that the רב אחאי's Rav Achai when it says פריך parich
or הוי בי רב אחאי havi be-Rav Achai was a later gloss
which was later inserted. What was רב אחאי גאון? Rav Achai Gaon?
It's like eighth-ninth century, so that's a good few hundred years later.
So again, I'm not sure exactly whether scholars agree that that's the
רב אחאי Rav Achai but clearly the language is always different, the
way it introduces it and the nature of the question is always
very tangential. So let's take a look. פריך רב אחאי, parich Rav
Achai, so רב אחאי Rav Achai says, nah, I don't buy that,
I don't buy that פטר חמור peter chamor by saying it twice
that excludes other animals because I have a way of reading the
verse otherwise. I could have said אי כתב רחמנא חד, i katav
rachamana chad, if it had just said פטר חמור peter chamor once,
הוי אמינא דבר שהיה בכלל ויצא מן הכלל ללמד לא ללמד על
עצמו יצא אלא ללמד על הכלל כולו יצא, havi amina davar shehayah
bichlal veyatza min haklal lilamed lo lilamed al atzmo yatza ela lilamed
al haklal kulo yatza, that normally what we say is something that
was part of a category that was singled out, we assume that
it's teaching not just it's not an exception, that's ללמד על עצמו,
lilamed al atzmo, but that it actually is teaching about the whole
category, ללמד על הכלל כולו. lilamed al haklal kulo. So first we
said all non-kosher animals redeem, then we said redeem the donkey gets
redeemed with a sheep. So I would have said that doesn't mean
just the donkey, that's an example, but it really means all non-kosher
animals you redeem with a sheep. So the first time it said
it I would have assumed that too limited to anything to donkeys,
I would have assumed it was an example, and then
ולעולם בשה, ul'olam beseh, everything would be with a sheep. אכתב רחמנא
פטר חמור אחרינא, akatav rachamana peter chamor achrina, and then it says
פטר חמור peter chamor second time to tell me פטרי חמורים ולא
פטרי סוסים וגמלים, pitrei chamorim velo pitrei susim ugemalim,
and that would,
that admittedly the second time would have limited it to a donkey,
but what would it have limited it to a donkey? The idea
of a sheep. ואימא מיעטינו משה, ve'eima mi'atinu miseh, it excludes other
animals from the sheep redemption ולעולם בכל דבר, ul'olam bechol davar, and
normally but it still anything else would be okay. Meaning you can't
say it says פטר חמור peter chamor twice to say it only
applies to donkeys. The first time would not have been a limiting,
the first time would have said there's a general idea of redeeming
with a sheep, the second time
would have limited the sheep idea to donkeys, but I still would
not have excluded the other animals, the other non-kosher animals. So how
can you do it just by saying it twice? So the גמרא
Gemara says back to this or whoever said back within this statement
of רב אחאי, Rav Achai, אם כן לכתוב רחמנא פטר חמור תפדה
בשה וחמור תפדה בשה, im ken lichtov rachamana peter chamor tifdeh veseh
vachamor tifdeh veseh, don't say the word פטר peter twice, just say
donkey redeem because we already know the context is firstborn. פטר חמור
תפדה בשה פטר חמור תפדה בשה למה לי? peter chamor tifdeh veseh
peter chamor tifdeh veseh lamma li? Why does it say פטר peter
twice?
So were those right next to each other?
I don't know, you'll have to go check it out. No, one
is in קדש לי, Kadesh Li, one is in שמות יג Shemot
Yud Gimmel and the other is in, is it in לד? Lamed
Dalet? So
yeah, but still, yeah, no, but at least both פסוקים pesukim are
in the context of firstborn so the argument is that it would
not have had to say פטר peter twice. So למה לי? lamma
li? So פטרי חמורים אמרתי לך ולא פטרי סוסים וגמלים, pitrei chamorim
amarti lecha velo pitrei susim ugemalim, to tell me only that of
donkeys, not of other animals. So with or without רב אחאי's Rav
Achai question, the basic פשט pshat is, is that what do you
do with the fact it says פטר חמור peter chamor twice? You
actually use it to tell me a very important part in terms
of פשט pshat of the פסוקים, pesukim, that although one פסוק pasuk
says very generically firstborn of non-kosher animals and we never exactly explain
why it makes such a broad generic statement, nevertheless the fact that
it says twice firstborn donkeys is to tell me that this whole
law only applies to donkeys. Not only the sheep aspect, but the
whole idea of redeeming of non-kosher animals only applies to donkeys. Now
the תנא דידן, tanna didan, now that that's such a good point
that needs to be made, how about the author of our משנה
Mishnah that uses פטר חמור peter chamor to tell me the mother
and child have to look like the donkey? למיעוטי סוסים וגמלים מנא
ליה, limutei susim ugemalim minalei, where do they know that the מצוה
mitzvah does not apply to horses and camels? אמר רב פפא amar
Rav Pappa
from another verse, כל מקנך תזכר, kol miknecha tizachar, it says all
of your of your flock you shall literally the word here is
תזכר, tizachar, male, but somehow we're learning it to mean take the
males and and treat them with this status of firstborn. born, so
that's כלל, klal, that's your entire flock. Then it says פטר שור
ושה, Peter shor vaseh, שור שה וחמור, shor seh vachamor, then then
afterwards it says, right, what's the פסוק? pasuk? כל מקנך תזכר פטר
שור ושה ופטר חמור תפדה בשה. Kol miknecha tizkar peter shor vaseh
upeter chamor tifdeh vaseh. Okay, so all of your animals take the
firstborn, it says that of the of the sheep and of the
flock, and then it says and of the firstborn of the donkey
you should redeem. So you have a כלל, klal, all, then you
have specifics,
sheep, cattle, flock, and donkey. So, so, ופטר חמור תפדה בשה, upeter
chamor tifdeh vaseh, כל מקנך תזכר Kol miknecha tizkar כלל, klal, שור
שה וחמור shor seh vachamor פרט, prat, כלל ופרט אין בכלל אלא
מה שבפרט. klal uprat ein baklal ela mah shebaprat.
So therefore it's a general and specific,
so the general is limited to the specific. שור שה וחמור Shor
seh vachamor אין, in, only only the cattle, the flock, and the
donkey, מידי אחריני לא, midei achrinei lo, nothing else. So you don't
learn it from an ex post facto that the תורה Torah repeated
it, but you use it from the fact that it appears in
the context of a כלל ופרט, klal uprat, which means that you
are you have nothing more than what is said in the פרט
prat and does not apply to anything more than the sheep, the
flock, and the donkey. So, רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGlili, why
why does רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili not learn it from
there? It's a general כלל ופרט, klal uprat, that should be a
good basis. No, פטר הפסיק הענין. peter hifsik hainyan. It says, right,
כל מקנך תזכר פטר שור ושה, Kol miknecha tizkar peter shor vaseh,
and then it says ופטר חמור תפדה בשה. upeter chamor tifdeh vaseh.
So that's a new פסוק, pasuk, right? It's a new statement. It's
not part of the previous כלל ופרט. klal uprat. So you can't
learn it as a כלל ופרט, klal uprat, it's a new sentence.
פטר הפסיק הענין, Peter hifsik hainyan, the second פטר peter breaks it
up and does not it's not connected to the previous general statement.
סברי רבנן, Savre rabanan, what do the רבנן rabanan say back? ו'
הדר ערביה קרא. Vav hadar arvei kra. It says ופטר חמור תפדה
בשה. upeter chamor tifdeh vaseh. So the ו', vav, although it's a
new sentence, the 'and' connects it to the previous, so it still
puts it in the context of the כלל ופרט. klal uprat. רבי
יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGlili, what does רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose
HaGlili say back? לא לכתוב לא ו' ולא פטר. Lo lichtov lo
vav velo peter. So if you wanted them to be to be
one sentence, don't write פטר peter and don't write the ו' vav
to connect it. So the fact that the תורה Torah wrote the
word פטר peter was to give it a status of a separate
sentence and not with the intention of connecting it, of having it
part of the same. If it wanted it part of the same,
it wouldn't have had the word פטר peter to begin with. One
minute, רבנן, rabanan, what do the רבנן rabanan say back? איידי דהא
קדושת דמים והא קדושת הגוף, Aidei deha kedushat damim veha kedushat haguf,
no, there was a desire to at least make somewhat separate statements
about them because the first case, פטר שור ושה, peter shor vaseh,
is intrinsic קדושה, kedusha, it's brought as a קרבן. korban. The second,
with the פטר חמור, peter chamor, is, I'm sorry, that's the קדושת
דמים. kedushat damim. The second, we're doing it in reverse order, the
second, the חמור chamor is קדושת דמים, kedushat damim, you only give
the value, the sheep to the כהן, kohen, it's never brought as
a קרבן. korban. The first half of the sentence is קדושת הגוף,
kedushat haguf, the שור shor oxen and the sheep are brought as
are brought as a קרבן. korban. So therefore פסיק להו, pasik lehu,
it wanted to have a verse, it wanted a way of starting
a new sentence. It's not all the same. One is you bring
it as a קרבן, korban, the other is you redeem it, right?
And actually the verb is different. It says, כל מקנך תזכר פטר
שור ושה, Kol miknecha tizkar peter shor vaseh, period, ופטר חמור תפדה,
upeter chamor tifdeh, right? The verb of redeeming is only going on
the donkey. So you had to make it a separate sentence, you
had to break it, so therefore you needed פטר peter was הפסיק
הענין, hifsik hainyan, פסיק
להו, pasik lehu, you needed to separate them. But because you still
wanted to make the general principle of כלל ופרט klal uprat and
say these are the only animals that you're ever obligated, then הדר
ערביה להו, hadar arvei lehu, then it went back and it combined
them with the ו'. vav. Okay, one minute, והדר ערביה להו, vehadar
arvei lehu, okay, and therefore we now know that the רבנן rabanan
learn out it's limited to donkeys by the כלל ופרט, klal uprat,
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose by the fact that it says פטר חמור
פטר חמור peter chamor peter chamor twice. But either way we are
what do you call it, either way we we know and we
address the fact that it is interesting that one פסוק pasuk makes
a very general statement, but at the end of the day we
limit it only to donkey. Why the פסוק pasuk made a general
statement, I still don't have an answer for you, Michael. Yes.
No, but you know what's interesting is though if we're saying we
need to have a separate sentence because we want to show that
one is קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, the other קדושת דמים, kedushat damim,
but the people get thrown in with the פטר חמור, peter chamor,
right? Yeah, because they're redeemed too. Right. Right, but they're not קדושת
הגוף kedushat haguf in the
sense that they get brought as a קרבן, korban, so they are
in the same קדושת דמים. kedushat damim. Anyway, if you want to
say it the way that you'd better, because the first half of
the פסוק pasuk you don't redeem and the second half you do
redeem, so you need to have them as separate halves of the
פסוק.
pasuk. ופטר חמור תפדה בשה. Upeter chamor tifdeh vaseh.
And right. Right.
So why do why doesn't anyone say that maybe you can also
redeem a person with a שה? seh?
You do redeem a person.
With a שה. seh.
No, whatever.
Because we don't want to. Yes, Charlie.
So they're talking about a different verse. Yeah. Are the verse they're
no
there's no punctuation in the חומש. Chumash. Right. But are the verses
were they the were the verse divisions determined by the sages or
is that right from משה רבינו? Moshe Rabbeinu?
Yeah, you know, that's a good question. I mean, part of the
there is okay, I there's there's a more complete answer to that
than I can give right now. First of all, without answering your
question, even without it being a separate verse, the fact is is
that there's a separate verb that's connected to it, ופטר חמור תפדה
בשה. upeter chamor tifdeh vaseh.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara seems to be focusing on, the
word is
the word of פטר, peter, not the fact the fact that it's
halachically, not the fact whether it is or not the same פסוק.
pasuk. The טראָפּ, trop, you know, there is a גמרא, Gemara, I'm
trying to remember,
you know, the whole question about the טראָפּ trop which ultimately is
what indicates also what a סוף פסוק sof pasuk is, right, was
a little bit indeterminate, you know, the גמרא Gemara says that there
are some פסוקים psukim we don't exactly know how to read the
טראָפּ trop and so on. On the other hand, the גמרא Gemara
has a principle about כל פסוק דלא פסקיה משה אנן לא פסקינן
kol pasuk d'lo paskei Moshe anan lo paskinan which, you know, any
פסוק pasuk that משה Moshe did not divide, we cannot divide, which
makes it, you know, sound very clear that we have a sense
that the what defines the פסוק pasuk is determined already by משה
רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu. So, but there is some question about the work
that the
Masorites, Masoretic, whatever, Masorites did
in terms of exactly nailing every little detail down. So the basic
answer, this is not a precise answer, I need to like refresh
my memory, but the basic answer is yes, the assumption is that
the מסורה Masorah is about all the divisions of the פסוקים, psukim,
whether that means that they that every single one did need a
little fine-tuning or not, you know, there wasn't a few questions here
or there might not, you know, is a separate question, but the
basic assumption, and then there's
kabbalistic notions that go beyond that, right?
Right, I mean the first רמב"ן Ramban on the תורה Torah in
the introduction, you know, is that the whole idea is that kabbalistically
you can re-divide the פסוקים psukim in any way and rearrange the
letters in any way and you know, recombine the words. So anyway,
okay. Because the well, the basic kabbalistic idea that the entire תורה
Torah is all one שם השם. Shem Hashem. Right. Okay anyway, alright,
moving on. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, איבעיא להו.
ibaya lehu. The
question was raised. פרה שילדה מין חמור ויש בו מקצת סימנים מהו.
Para sheyalda min chamor v'yesh bo miktzat simanim mahu. So now we
have said before that if a sheep gives birth to a goat,
something that looks like a goat, or vice-versa, it does not have
קדושת בכור. kdushat bechor. But if it has some of the characteristics
of the right species, so a sheep gives birth to something that
looks like a half-goat, half-sheep, because it looks like a half-sheep and
the mother is a sheep, that's enough to obligate it in בכור.
bechor. We actually also said a few days ago that it would
still be considered a בעל מום, baal mum, but nevertheless it had
קדושת בכור. kdushat bechor. Now we want to know, can you transfer
that idea to the donkey case? Because we've spoken about a donkey
giving birth to something that looks like, I don't know, a camel,
but we've never spoken about the case of looking half and half.
So let's take a look. So איבעיא להו, ibaya lehu, they raised
the question. פרה שילדה מין חמור ויש בו מקצת סימנים. Para sheyalda
min chamor v'yesh bo miktzat simanim. Okay, so first we're actually asking
about a cow that gives birth to something that looks like a
donkey but has some cow characteristics. Okay, is that enough that it's
a cow that gives birth to something that is quasi-cow, is that
enough to obligate it in a בכור? bechor? מהו, mahu, what's the
rule? עז שילדה מן רחל רחל שילדה מן עז, Ez sheyalda min
rachel rachel sheyalda min ez, we know by the goat giving birth
to the sheep and the sheep into the goat, דכי יש מקצת
סימנים חייב בבכורה, dechi yesh miktzat simanim chayav bivchora, as long as
it has some characteristics like the mother, it's still obligated. But that's
because everything is in the same פרשה, parsha, דהא טהור והא טהור,
de'ha tahor ve'ha tahor, they're both kosher animals, a goat and a
sheep. הא קדושת הגוף והא קדושת הגוף, ha kdushat haguf ve'ha kdushat
haguf, and they both are intrinsic sanctity, they're both would be brought
as a קרבן. korban. So therefore, since it's all basically the exact
same פרשה, parsha, as long as it has some of the סימנים
simanim like the mother,
then it would be enough. Just remembering that joke that Dov sent
out before שבת. Shabbat. Did people get that email
that what was it, how was it, something like Laban or Bethuel
says to Rivka, we gotta get you married, and she says but
I'm only three years old. He says yeah, but you're in the
פרשה. parsha. Alright, so anyway, so as long as it's in the
פרשה parsha here, right, they're all kosher animals, they're all brought as
a בכור bechor etc. So as long as it looks some of
the characteristics of the right species, that would be enough. Okay, so
דהא טהור והא קדושת הגוף. אבל הכא, avel hacha, but here, דהא
טמא והא טהור, de'ha tamei ve'ha tahor,
the cow gave birth to something that looks like a donkey, one
is kosher, one's not kosher. הא קדושת הגוף והא קדושת דמים. ha
kdushat haguf ve'ha kdushat damim. It's interesting, it reverses the order here.
Anyway, the one has an intrinsic sanctity, the cow, and the donkey
is only the value. So they're basically, although they're both in the
category of בכור, bechor, they're fundamentally different types of בכור. bechor. So
there, even if it has some characteristics of the right species, לא,
lo, would I say that that's not
enough since the other part of it looks so fundamentally different and
is so much in a different category? או דלמא, o dilma, perhaps
I would say, כיון דאידי ואידי במקדש בבכורה, keivan de'eidi ve'eidi bemikdash
bivchora, since at least both of them are in the category of
בכור, bechor, one as a cow, one as a donkey, קדוש, kadosh,
they're enough and it's enough relevant, so therefore the somewhat the the
the
some characteristics of the right species is enough to make it make
it קדוש. kadosh. That's one possibility. He said, what would I say
by cow with a donkey where the some of the characteristics are
cow-like?
ואם תמצא לומר, ve'im timtza lomar, and if you were to grant
me that point and say, כיון דאידי ואידי במקדש בבכורה קדוש, keivan
de'eidi ve'eidi bemikdash bivchora kadosh, that since both of them are in
the בכור bechor category, although one as a kosher, one as a
non-kosher animal, therefore the some of the quasi- characteristics is enough to
make it holy. So חמור שילדה כמין סוס מהו. Chamor sheyalda kemin
sus mahu. Let's say that the one of the child is not
at all in the בכור bechor category. A donkey gives birth to
something that looks like a horse. And again, some of the characteristics
are like a
donkey. Will the partial characteristics be enough to keep it in the
category, given that the other part of it looks like something completely
out of the category? הכא ודאי לא בת מקדש בבכור היא. Hacha
vadai lo bat mikdash bevchor hi. Here we would say certainly a
horse is not at all in the category of the firstborn. No,
this is with some partial characteristics like the mother, some partial donkey
characteristics. So because the child is, some part of it is completely
out of the category, the partial characteristics don't redeem it, don't, I
don't mean redeem literally here, don't make it included. או דלמא, O
dilma, or do we say, כיון דמין טמא הוא, kivan demin tamei
hu, since they're both non-kosher animals, they're enough related to one another
and it does have some of the correct characteristics, so קדוש kadosh
it would be enough to have the sanctity of a בכור bechor
as a donkey. אם תמצא לומר כיון דמין טמא הוא קדוש, Im
timtza lomar kivan demin tamei hu kadosh, if you say that in
that case they're at least similar enough that the partial characteristics put
it in the category, so how about if it's really as far
away from one another as possible? פרה שילדה כמין סוס מהו. Parah
sheyalda kemin sus mahu. If a cow gives birth to something that
looks like a horse with some cow characteristics. So the horse aspect
is totally different from the cow. Number one, kosher, non-kosher. Number two,
one is in the category of בכור bechor and the second is
totally out. So will there the somewhat partial cow characteristics be enough
to keep it included? Will we say הכא ודאי הטמא והטהור, hacha
vadai hatamei vehatahor, here definitely they're different, one is kosher, the other
is not kosher. הא בת מקדש בבכור, ha bat mikdash bevchor, the
cow is in the category of firstborn, והא לא בת מקדש בבכור,
veha lo bat mikdash bevchor, and the horse is not. או דלמא,
O dilma, or would we say, סימנים מילתא היא. simanim milta hi.
No, as long as some of the characteristics are enough, that's enough
to make it in the category. Yes, that סימנים מילתא היא simanim
milta hi is used from a totally different context. But here basically
it's asking the following thing. We taught by the sheep and the
goat that if a sheep gives birth to something that looks like
a goat, it's excluded, but if it has somewhat sheep characteristics, it's
included. So now the גמרא Gemara is saying, is it just those
characteristics enough that are enough to say that the child is connected
to the mother, is the right type of a child and it's
obligated, or does it also require that the other thing that it
looks like also be somewhat relevant to this whole category or not,
or is it just by those partial characteristics that's enough?
Are we not wondering about people? What?
Oh, let's, we'll get to people later. תא שמע, Ta shema, come
and hear. בהמה טהורה שילדה כמין בהמה טמאה פטורה מן הבכורה. Behemah
tehorah sheyalda kemin behemah temeah peturah min habechorah. So we have a
ברייתא braita that says a kosher animal that gives birth to something
that looks, I'm sorry, a kosher animal that gives birth to a
non-kosher animal is exempt from בכורה. bechorah. אם יש בה מקצת סימנים
חייבת בבכורה. Im yesh bah miktzat simanim chayaves bevchorah. But if it
has some of the right characteristics, even some of them, it's obligated.
And there it said non-kosher animal, presumably it's including all
things. מאי לאו אפילו פרה שילדה כמין סוס. Mai lav afilu parah
sheyalda kemin sus. Isn't this not talking about even our last case,
our most extreme case, a cow gives birth to something that looks
like a horse, and nevertheless if some of the characteristics are correct,
it's
obligated? גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, no, not necessarily. פרה שילדה כמין
חמור. Parah sheyalda kemin chamor. Maybe it's talking about when it says
a non-kosher animal, it means the right type of non-kosher animal, a
donkey. So if a cow gives birth to a donkey and it
has some of the right characteristics. But at least we've answered our
first question, right? Our first question was the least extreme was a
cow giving birth to something that looks like a donkey. They're both
in the בכור bechor category, although different types of בכור bechor category.
So at least that we said in that case having partial סימנים
simanim is enough. But we don't know about our next two questions.
תא שמע, Ta shema, so come in here, we're going to try
again. פרה שילדה כמין חמור וחמור שילדה כמין סוס. Parah sheyalda kemin
chamor vechamor sheyalda kemin sus. A cow gives birth to something that
looks like a donkey, so that we've already resolved, or a donkey
gives birth to something that looks like a horse. Okay, so that
is, that is the second question where the second thing is not
in the בכור bechor category, it's a horse, but at least they're
both non-kosher animals. פטור מן הבכורה. Patur min habechorah. In that case
you're exempt. אם יש בו מקצת סימנים חייבת בבכורה. Im yesh bo
miktzat simanim chayaves bevchorah. And if it has some of the right
characteristics, you're obligated. מאי לאו אדוייהו, Mai lav aduvaihu, is that not
modifying both cases and even the case of a donkey giving birth
to a horse? So you see even in that middle case partial
סימנים simanim is enough to obligate you. גמרא Gemara says לא, lo,
no, אפרה שילדה כמין חמור, aparah sheyalda kemin chamor, only the first
case about the cow and the donkey which we've already conceded that
the cow-donkey case partial סימנים simanim would obligate you because at least
both of those are in the בכור bechor category.
So the question is after the second one, it goes, I
know, it's a little funny. אבל חמור שילדה כמין סוס למאי קתני
לה. Aval chamor sheyalda kemin sus lemai katani lah. So the גמרא
Gemara says, so one minute, if that's true, why did it even
bother with the second case about a donkey that gave birth to
a horse? לפטורא, Leptura, to just to tell me that you're exempt?
פשיטא, Pshita, of course you're exempt. השתא מה פרה שילדה כמין חמור,
Hashta mah parah sheyalda kemin chamor, when the cow gave birth to
the donkey, דאידי ואידי בני מקדש בבכור נינהו, de'idi ve'idi benei mikdash
bevchor ninhu, that they're both in the category of בכור, bechor, אמרת
אם יש בו מקצת סימנים אין ואי לא לא, amart im yesh
bo miktzat simanim in ve'i lo lo, you say it's only obligated
if it has some of the right characteristics, but normally... A cow
that gave birth to a donkey would be exempt, so once you've
told me that, that a cow and a cow donkey is exempt,
חמור שילדה מין סוס מיבעיא? chamor she-yaldah min sus mi-ba'aya? So of
course a donkey giving birth to a horse, where they're totally different,
of course it would be exempt. So since it bothered to give
me that second case, it must be it's giving it to me
only to teach me that when it has some of the right
סימנין, simanin, you're obligated even though it's a donkey-horse. So גמרא Gemara
says no, not necessarily, איצטריך, itzterich, I need it. סלקא דעתך אמינא,
salka da'atach amina, I would have thought התם הוא דיש לו קרניים
והא אין לו קרניים. hasam hu de-yesh lo karnayim ve-ha ein lo
karnayim. I would have thought that even though it's true that cow
and donkey are both in the בכור bechor category, maybe you're, you
know, maybe the donkey and the horse are more logically obligated than
cow and donkey. Why? Basically
because cow and donkey are very different from one another. One's a
kosher and one's a non-kosher animal. So maybe that you're exempt, but
maybe donkey-horse, maybe you're obligated because they're both non-kosher animals and they
look much more similar. A donkey and a horse does look much
more similar.
One minute. התם הוא דיש לו קרניים והא אין לו קרניים. hasam
hu de-yesh lo karnayim ve-ha ein lo karnayim. So a cow has
horns, a donkey doesn't have
horns. הא פרסותיו סדוקות, ha parsotav sedukot, a cow has cleft hooves,
והא אין פרסותיו סדוקות. ve-ha ein parsotav sedukot. הא, excuse me, הא
פרסותיו קלוטות, and by the donkey the hooves are combined. אבל הכא,
aval hacha, so therefore, of course you're exempt by a cow and
a donkey even though they're both in the בכור bechor category because
they're so physically different. But I might have thought אבל הכא aval
hacha by the case of the donkey and the
horse, דאידי ואידי אין לו קרניים, de-idi ve-idi ein lo karnayim, neither
have horns, דאידי ואידי פרסותיו קלוטות, de-idi ve-idi parsotav klutot, and both
have single hooves, אימא חמור אדום בעלמא הוא, eima chamor adom be-alma
hu, I might have just thought that even though it looks like
a horse, it's not really a horse, it's just like a reddish
donkey. Apparently horses were red or the horses they used to have
were red. So I would not have thought it's really different. קמשמע
לן kamashma lan that it is different enough to be considered to
be different. Now of course the upside of this is that first
of all, even though you told me that a horse and a
donkey is exempt, you still have to tell me that a, I'm
sorry, that a cow and a donkey is exempt, you still have
to tell me that a donkey and a horse is exempt because
I might have thought donkey and horse are, maybe the thing that
looks like a horse is fundamentally a donkey, which we know genetically
it is anyway, but okay. So it's telling me that that's exempt.
Now I know that all these things when it doesn't look like
the same species is exempt. What about partial characteristics? I know partial
characteristics is enough to obligate it by sheep and goat because they're
both in the same category. How about by things that are in
different categories? So the one thing we have proven is that partial
characteristics, if it's the case of a cow and donkey, since they're
both in the בכור bechor category, if the donkey has some cow-like
characteristics, it is obligated. Our other two questions we have not resolved.
So if it's the donkey that gives birth to something that looks
like a horse, or if it's a cow that gives birth to
something that looks like a horse, will partial characteristics of the mother
be enough to obligate it? That remains as an unresolved question. The
question with all of these, of course, is whether the גמרא Gemara
actually thinks that the thing that is being born is literally another
species, right, or just is it saying that no, it is a
donkey but it looks like a horse and that's enough to exempt
it? That gets never, that doesn't really get fully explored. Yes, Charlie.
When they're talking about is it obligated בכור, bechor, are they talking
about the need for redemption or for the kosher animals offering it
on the altar?
Oh, so if the mother is the חמור chamor and then you
say the child has some חמור chamor characteristics, so then we would
talk about redeeming it. If the mother is a kosher animal and
we talk about if the child has some of the characteristics, then
it would be for קדושת קרבן, kedushat korban, but as the גמרא
Gemara said earlier, even if I can see that it has a
קדושה kedusha because of partial characteristics, the fact that it looks so
different makes it a בעל מום. baal mum. So in the end
of the day you would still give it to a כהן, kohen,
it would be eaten without being brought as a קרבן, korban, but
with the limits of קדושת בכור kedushat bechor which we'll find about
later.
Now all this is when both the mother and the father are
of the same species. But let's say you have a father horse
or something like that and a mother whatever, you know. Like does
the father, you know what I mean, does that change anything?
We'll get to that later about whether חוששין לזרע האב chosheshin le-zera
ha-av or not. I mean for now we're just, right now we're
not even questioning parentage even in theoretically if both parents were the
right species, the fact that the child looks different is enough to
exempt it. Okay, what would be the story when the parent is
of a different species? There's a משנה, mishna, trust me, we'll get
to it.
Okay, so I just want to make sure I understood where we
got to. So we basically said that if let's say a cow
gives birth to like something that looks like a sheep, it looks
totally like a sheep, then you don't do it at all, right?
It looks somewhat like a cow still, then it does as a,
then at
least in the case of kosher and kosher, if it has some
of the characteristics of the mother, it has its קדושת בכור, kedushat
bechor, although it's considered a בעל מום, baal mum, and the case
about,
and the one case we conceded here was the same was true
about a cow and a donkey. If a cow gives birth to
something that looks like a donkey, or presumably the reverse, and had
some of the partial characteristics, it would also have the same as
before, but none, it would always be out, and then if it
was anything other than kosher-kosher or cow-donkey or whatever, then we don't
know. אין טמא tamei. הנולד מן הטהור טמא tamei. (ve'ein tamei hanolad
min hatahor tamei) אלא ella, טהור (ella tahor) The speaker says "Umah
hen ba'achilah" ומה הן באכילה. Umah hen ba'achilah? The speaker says "yotzei
min hatamei tamei, yotzei min hatahor tahor" יוצא מן הטמא טמא, yotzei
min hatamei tamei, יוצא מן הטהור טהור. The speaker says "kedushat bechor"
קדושת בכור.
The speaker says "treifah" טריפה. The speaker says "treifot" טריפות.
The speaker says "shecht" שחט. The speaker says "rov" רוב. The speaker
says "matzui" מצוי. The speaker says "lo shechiach" לא שכיח. The speaker
says "lamah li lemasni" למה לי למתני. The speaker says "shehayotzei min
hatamei tamei vehayotzei min hatahor tahor" שהיוצא מן הטמא
טמא והיוצא מן הטהור טהור. The speaker says "simana be'alma hu" סימנא
בעלמא הוא. The speaker says "delo tachalof lach" דלא תחלוף לך. The
speaker says "delo teima זיל
בתר דידיה" דלא תימא זיל בתר דידיה. The speaker says "vehai tahor
ma'alya hu" והאי טהור מעליא הוא. The speaker says "vehai tamei ma'alya
hu" והאי טמא מעליא הוא. The speaker says "zil batar imei" זיל
בתר אימיה. The speaker says "mana hanei milei" מנא הני מילי. The
speaker says "detanu רבנן" Rabbanan, דתנו רבנן. The speaker says "Ach et
zeh lo tochlu" אך את et זה לא תאכלו. The speaker says
"ach et zeh lo tochlu ממעלי הגרה וממפריסי הפרסה" אך את et?
זה לא תאכלו ממעלי הגרה וממפריסי הפרסה. The speaker says "yesh lecha
shehu ma'aleh gerah umafris parsah" יש לך שהוא מעלה גרה ומפריס פרסה.
The speaker
says "ve'i atah ochlo" ואי אתה אוכלו. The speaker says "ve'eizeh zeh"
ואיזה זה. The speaker says "zeh טהור שנולד מן הטמא" זה טהור
שנולד מן הטמא. The speaker says "o eino ella tamei hanolad min
hatahor" או אינו אלא ella, טמא הנולד מן הטהור. The speaker says
"umah ממעלי הגרה וממפריסי הפרסה" ומהי ממעלי הגרה וממפריסי הפרסה. The speaker
says "hachi ka'amar" הכי קאמר. The speaker says "davar haba ממעלה גרה
וממפריס הפרסה" דבר הבא ממעלה גרה וממפריס הפרסה. The speaker says "lo
tochal" לא תאכל. The speaker says "talmud lomar" תלמוד לומר. The speaker
says "gamal tamei hu" גמל Gamal טמא הוא. The speaker says "hu
tamei" הוא טמא. The speaker says "ve'ein tamei hanolad min hatahor tamei"
ואין טמא הנולד מן הטהור טמא. The speaker says "ella tahor" אלא
ella, טהור. One small thing: "Umah hen ba'achilah" ומה הן באכילה. The
speaker says "Umah hen ba'achilah" at the very beginning. "Okay, so now
the Gemara goes on. ומה הן באכילה? Now we actually
turn..." Wait, the speaker says "Umah hen ba'achilah" twice in the chunk.
Once at the start, once later. "Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. ומה הן באכילה? What's the story..." Yes, I have both.
Final check on "no line breaks". The output must be one single
block. One more check on the Hebrew: - ומה הן באכילה (Umah
hen ba'achilah) - יוצא מן הטמא טמא yotzei min hatamei tamei. (yotzei
min hatamei tamei) - יוצא מן הטהור טהור (yotzei min hatahor tahor)
- משנה mishna (Mishnah) - קדושת בכור (kedushat bechor) - כשר (kosher)
- קדושה (kedushah) - טריפה (treifah) - טריפות (treifot) - שחט (shecht)
- רוב (rov) - מצוי (matzui) - לא שכיח (lo shechiach) -
גמרא Gemara (Gemara) - למה לי למתני (lamah li lemasni) - שהיוצא
מן הטמא טמא והיוצא מן הטהור טהור (shehayotzei min hatamei tamei vehayotzei
min hatahor tahor) - סימנא בעלמא הוא (simana be'alma hu) דלא תחלוף
לך (delo tachalof lach) דלא תימא זיל בתר דידיה (delo teima zil
batar dideih) והאי טהור מעליא הוא (vehai tahor ma'alya hu) והאי טמא
מעליא הוא (vehai tamei ma'alya hu) אלא (Ella) זיל בתר אימיה (Zil
batar imei) מנא הני מילי (mana hanei milei) דתנו רבנן (detanu rabanan)
אך את et. זה לא תאכלו (Ach et zeh lo tochlu) פסוק
pasuk (pasuk) אך את et. זה לא תאכלו ממעלי הגרה וממפריסי הפרסה
(ach et zeh lo tochlu ממעלי הגרה וממפריסי הפרסה)
יש לך שהוא מעלה
גרה ומפריס פרסה (yesh lecha shehu מעלה גרה ומפריס פרסה) ואי אתה
אוכלו (ve'i atah
ochlo) ואיזה זה (ve'eizeh zeh) ואיזה (ve'eizeh) זה טהור שנולד מן הטמא
(zeh טהור שנולד מן הטמא) או אינו אלא טמא הנולד מן הטהור
(o eino ella tamei hanolad
min hatahor) ומהי ממעלי הגרה וממפריסי הפרסה (umah ממעלי הגרה וממפריסי הפרסה)
הכי קאמר (hachi ka'amar) דבר הבא ממעלה גרה וממפריס הפרסה (davar haba
ממעלה גרה
וממפריס הפרסה) לא תאכל (lo tochal) תלמוד לומר (talmud lomar) גמל gamal
טמא הוא (gamal tamei hu) טמא (tamei) הוא טמא (hu tamei) הוא
(hu) ואין טמא הנולד מן הטהור טמא
(ve'ein tamei hanolad min hatahor tamei) אלא טהור (ella tahor) The speaker
says "Umah hen ba'achilah" ומה הן באכילה. The speaker says "yotzei min
hatamei tamei, yotzei min hatahor tahor" יוצא מן הטמא טמא, יוצא מן
הטהור טהור. The speaker says "kedushat bechor" קדושת בכור. The speaker says
"treifah" טריפה. The speaker says "treifot" טריפות. The speaker says "shecht" שחט.
The speaker says "rov" רוב. The speaker says "matzui" מצוי. The speaker
says "lo shechiach" לא שכיח. The speaker says "lamah li lemasni" למה
לי למתני. The speaker says "shehayotzei min hatamei tamei vehayotzei min hatahor
tahor" שהיוצא מן הטמא טמא והיוצא מן הטהור טהור. The speaker says
"simana be'alma hu" סימנא
בעלמא הוא. The speaker says "delo tachalof lach" דלא תחלוף לך. The
speaker says "delo teima זיל בתר דידיה" דלא תימא זיל בתר דידיה.
The speaker says "vehai tahor ma'alya hu" והאי טהור מעליא הוא. The
speaker says "vehai tamei ma'alya hu" והאי
טמא מעליא הוא. The speaker says "zil batar imei" זיל בתר אימיה.
The speaker says "mana hanei milei" מנא הני מילי. The speaker says
"detanu רבנן" דתנו רבנן. The speaker says "Ach et zeh lo tochlu"
אך
את et זה לא תאכלו. The speaker says "ach et zeh lo
tochlu ממעלי הגרה וממפריסי הפרסה" אך את et? זה לא תאכלו ממעלי
הגרה וממפריסי הפרסה. The speaker says "yesh lecha shehu מעלה
גרה ומפריס פרסה" יש לך שהוא מעלה גרה ומפריס פרסה. The speaker
says "ve'i atah ochlo" ואי אתה אוכלו. The speaker says "ve'eizeh zeh"
ואיזה זה. The speaker says "zeh טהור שנולד מן הטמא" זה טהור
שנולד מן
הטמא. The speaker says "o eino ella tamei hanolad min hatahor" או
אינו אלא טמא הנולד מן הטהור. The speaker says "umah ממעלי הגרה
וממפריסי הפרסה" ומהי ממעלי הגרה וממפריסי הפרסה. The speaker says "hachi ka'amar"
הכי קאמר. The speaker says "davar haba
ממעלה גרה וממפריס הפרסה" דבר הבא ממעלה גרה וממפריס הפרסה. The speaker
says "lo tochal" לא תאכל. The speaker says
"talmud lomar" תלמוד לומר. The speaker says "gamal tamei hu" גמל gamal
טמא הוא. The speaker says "hu tamei" הוא טמא. The speaker says
"ve'ein tamei hanolad min hatahor tamei" ואין טמא הנולד מן הטהור טמא.
The speaker says "ella tahor" אלא טהור. The question is not what
it looks like, but where it came from. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
אומר גמל גמל gamal gamal, שני פעמים. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon actually
disagrees. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says it does matter what it looks
like. It says גמל gamal twice, once obviously in ויקרא Vayikra once
in דברים, Devarim, two totally separate times it repeats the פרשה parsha
of kosher non-kosher animals, to tell you the following: אחד גמל הנולד
מן הגמלה ואחד גמל הנולד מן הפרה, echad gamal hanolad min hagamala
ve'echad gamal hanolad min hapara, whether its mother was a camel, a
camelist, a camela, I don't know, or whether the mother was a
cow, what's a female camel? Anyway, so whether the mother was a
cow, either way it's not kosher. So he actually says you do
go by what it looks like. Presumably he only says this to
be strict, not to be lenient. We've never heard that he says
that if something was born from a camel that looks like a
cow, it's kosher. But he says if it looks like a camel,
that is enough to make it non-kosher even if the mother is
a cow. Interesting questions, right? They're always asking the question about what
happens if you in a laboratory, you know, make a pig? Right?
So it wasn't born by a mother pig. Okay, so according to
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel at least, presumably it would be not kosher
because it doesn't matter what the mother is as long as it
has all the non-kosher סימנים. simanim. רבנן,
the Rabbis, האי גמל גמל מאי עביד ליה? hai gamal gamal mai
avid lei? They don't read it that way. So what do they
do with the fact it says camel twice, since they say it
just goes by the mother? So they say חד לאסור עצמו וחד
לאסור חלבו. chad le'asor atzmo vechad le'asor chalavo. Now we are going,
not חלבו chelbo but חלבו, chalavo, it's milk. Now we are moving
to from this to the second part of the discussion about byproducts.
So it says camel twice to tell you not only is a
camel not kosher, but camel milk is not kosher, which is basically
the second point of יוצא מן הטמא טמא, even the byproducts are
טמא. ורבי שמעון, VeRebbi Shimon, what would רבי Rebbi, שמעון say? לאסור
חלבו מנא ליה? le'asor chalavo minalei? Where does he know the milk
of a camel's not kosher? נפקא ליה מאת הגמל, nafka lei mei'et
hagamal, because it says את הגמל, et hagamal, the camel, so the
את et. means something that's connected to the camel but not the
camel itself, a byproduct of the camel, the milk. ורבנן, VeRabbanan, what
do the Rabbis do with the את? es את לא דרשי, et
lo darshi, they don't feel they have to interpret the word את.
es. They're not bothered by their את. כי דתניא, ki d'tanya, and
it's always fun when the גמרא Gemara uses this as an opportunity
to bring in this
ברייתא. baraita. שמעון העמסוני היה דורש כל את ואת שבתורה. Shimon Ha'amsuni
haya doresh kol et ve'et shebaTorah. שמעון העמסוני Shimon Ha'amsuni would דרשן
darshen every single time it said את in the תורה Torah to
include something that was connected to the thing itself. We're getting there.
כיון שהגיע לאת ה' אלהיך תירא, keivan shehigia le'et Hashem Elokecha tira,
he got to the פסוק pasuk, you should fear ה' Hashem your
God, פירש, pirash, he separated, he said I can't, nothing is comparable
to fear of God. And presumably what it means is not only
what did he not interpret that פסוק, pasuk, he figured my whole
system is wrong now because I see there's no way of interpreting
that פסוק, pasuk, so therefore I have to give up on the
whole enterprise. So אמרו לו תלמידיו, amru lo talmidav, so his students
said to him, רבי, Rebbi. כל אתין שדרשת מה תהא עליהם? kol
etin she'darashta ma tehei aleihem? What about all those דרשות drashas you
learned out from את? What are you going to do now that
you're reversing yourself? אמר להם, amar lahem, he said to them, כשם
שקבלתי שכר על הדרישה כך אני מקבל שכר על הפרישה. keshem shekibalti
sachar al hadrisha kach ani mekabel sachar al haprisha. The same way
I received reward for the interpreting and the expositing, I'll receive reward
for now stepping back. And yes, I have to sacrifice that, but
that's what it means to, you know, to have intellectual integrity and
to when interpreting the תורה. Torah.
So this was something that was not received from his teachers. Right?
Yes.
And that's valid to...
Sure, I mean there's a general question which
is, let me get back, let's finish the story, I don't want
to lose the momentum, I'll get back to you in a minute.
עד שבא רבי עקיבא ולמד, ad sheba Rebbi Akiva velimmad, and then
רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva came and he figured out how to read
the את. את ה' אלהיך תירא, et Hashem Elokecha tira, לרבות תלמידי
חכמים, lerabbot talmidei chachamim, to include תורה Torah scholars. So the question
is what, שמעון העמסוני Shimon Ha'amsuni couldn't figure that out? So there's
a beautiful answer which is that he could not imagine that you
could ever have that sense of מורא, mora, of a מורא mora
of a רב rav that is equal to מורא שמים. mora shamayim.
But when רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva saw what that שמעון העמסוני's Shimon
Ha'amsuni intellectual integrity, that he was prepared to sacrifice his life's labor
for the sake of, you know, a sense of אמת emet in
interpreting the תורה, Torah, then רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva said you know
there are some תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim that you could כביכול kiveyakhol
compare to מורא שמים. mora shamayim. So that's a nice little, that's
I can't take credit for that, I forget where I originally heard
that, but anyway, that's a nice way to speak about what it
means to have real integrity in the process. In terms of Dov's
question, which is do you need a מסורה? mesora? The גמרא Gemara
says you need a מסורה mesora for גזירה שוה. gezeira shava. Although
even there that's somewhat questionable as the רמבן Ramban asks in his
השגות hassagot on the רמבם's Rambam ספר המצות, Sefer HaMitzvot, he says
what do you mean you need a מסורה mesora for גזירה שוה?
gezeira shava? The גמרא Gemara sometimes says well why do you learn
the גזירה שוה gezeira shava this פסוק, pasuk? why don't you learn
it that פסוק? pasuk What do you mean? I had my מסורה
mesora from my רבי. So the רמבן Ramban says even when we
say גזירה שוה's gezeira shava מסורה, mesora, what it means is that
you really have the הלכה halacha in the מסורה mesora and you
have a מסורה mesora that it's possible to learn it out from
a גזירה שוה, gezeira shava, but you have to go figure out
the גזירה שוה gezeira shava yourself. So that's even qualifying what it
even means to say גזירה שוה's gezeira shava מסורה. mesora. The גמרא
Gemara also says at the other end that a קל וחומר kal
vachomer is an אדם דורש מעצמו adam doresh mei'atzmo because... That's just
a logical derivation. Although knowing how the גמרא Gemara does קל וחומר
Kal V'chomer is sometimes they don't always seem to be exactly sort
of our system of a pure of a pure logical derivation, but
anyway the גמרא Gemara says קל וחומר Kal V'chomer דורש מעצמו. dorish
me'atzmo. The question is everything in between, the thing that is the
most arbitrary, which is גזרה שוה, Gezeira Shava, and the most logical,
which is קל וחומר, Kal V'chomer, can you do that on your
own or do you need a מסורה? mesorah? So that actually is
debated רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafos. I think רש"י Rashi basically says
that pretty much other than קל וחומר Kal V'chomer you need a
מסורה mesorah for everything, and תוספות Tosafos says that that no, other
than other than גזרה שוה Gezeira Shava everything else you can do
on your own. So clearly it does seem like there was much
more latitude and you know as I said even by גזרה שוה
Gezeira Shava what you mean that you need a מסורה mesorah is
somewhat questionable. I was just going to say תוספות Tosafos certainly will
expound things that people had not expounded. Well that's true too, but
not necessarily דרשות פסוקים. drashos pesukim. Yes. So again with this גמל
and גמלא, gamala, so again the fathers another משנה Mishnah, coming up,
but you know the father's input into this is makes no difference.
In other words you could say yes, we are not talking right
now, we will deal with different we'll deal with the father later.
Now we can assume that you either you either you only go
by the mother or that or that the father is of the
same species. That's right now irrelevant to the discussion. Okay,
so now we have said we had this nice little digression, but
ר' גמליאל Rabbi Gamliel but ר' יוסי Rabbi Yose learns out from
was it ר' יוסי? Rabbi Yose? I forget. ר' שמעון Rabbi Shimon
learns out from את the idea of milk. And the Rabbis learn
out from the extra גמל the idea of milk, but we have
the idea that a byproduct of a non-kosher animal is also not
kosher. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה רב
אחא בריה דרב אשי Amar lei Rav Acha brei de'Rav Ashi אלא
מעתה. ela me'ata. So רב אחא בריה דרב Rav Acha brei de'Rav
said to רב אשי Rav Ashi given that טעמא דרבנן מגמל גמל,
ta'ama de'rabbanan mi'gamal gamal, דר' שמעון מאת גמל, de'Rabbi Shimon mei'es gamal,
the Rabbis learn out from the double גמל that the milk is
not kosher and ר' שמעון Rabbi Shimon learns it out from the
את. הלאו הכי Halav hachi were it not for that הוה אמינא
hava amina I would have thought חלב דבהמה טמאה שרי, chalav de'beheima
tmeia sharei, that the fat excuse me that the milk of a
non-kosher animal would be permissible. I would not have said that a
byproduct is forbidden. So one minute, מאי שנא מהא דתניא, mai shna
mei'ha de'tanya, how would it be different from that which we taught
הטמאים hatme'im right we have this in חולין Chullin these are the
things that are not kosher so the extra ה hei is coming
to say לאסור צירן ורוטבן וקיפה שלהם, le'asur tziran v'rotban v'kipa shelahem,
to forbid their sort of their brine especially if it's like fish,
the fish brine, the stuff the juices that come up from the
fattiness of the fish or their sauce or the קיפה, kipa, קיפה
kipa is like their the mushy you know like if the stuff
that's the gook on the bottom of the pot. Of course one
wonders why you even need a חידוש chiddush for that if that's
really just fish gook. So תוספות Tosafos says part of it maybe
you don't need a חידוש chiddush for the end of it, it's
just thrown in. Maybe the חידוש chiddush at the end is that
even if something is in somewhat liquefied form and it's you know
it started by a solid that's now liquid you might say that's
not considered eating, it doesn't matter even if you ingest it by
drinking. But our focus is on the first half of it where
it says their brine, the stuff you know the the juices that
come out of it. So you see that that's forbidden. So therefore
the milk would be the same. Now of course there's a big
difference because תוספות Tosafos always asks and you know it he doesn't
really ever resolve why do you need a דרשה drasha to say
like fish brine is forbidden? What about the general principle that טעם
כעיקר ta'am k'ikar is forbidden? Anything right if I go ahead and
cook this טריף treif fish in water, the water's forbidden if it
has the taste of the טריף treif fish. How much more so
is the brine forbidden? So could be that maybe it's more forbidden
there's a debate if טעם כעיקר ta'am k'ikar is דאורייתא, d'oraisa, this
is definitely biblical or could be that you know could be that
טעם כעיקר ta'am k'ikar although it's forbidden is only forbidden with like
an עשה, asei, this maybe is forbidden with a לא תעשה. lo
ta'asei. But anyway it's a general question. But the point is is
that fish brine tastes like fish. Okay, at least it has a
very fishy taste. Camel's milk does not I'm betting does not taste
too much like camel. How much does milk taste like camel? All
right, so just because you say fish brine that type of a
byproduct is forbidden does not mean every byproduct is forbidden. But the
גמרא Gemara nevertheless asks this question, why do I need to say
that milk is forbidden? I already know from הטמאים hatme'im that these
types of byproducts general byproducts are forbidden. Okay,
yeah the blood not qua blood but you mean like qua as
a byproduct of a non-kosher
animal. Yes. Anyway the גמרא Gemara says איצטריך, itztrich, I needed a
separate verse by milk. Why? סלקא דעתך אמינא Salaka daitach amina
I would have thought הואיל דבהמה טהורה נמי חידוש הוא ho'il de'beheima
tehora nami chiddush hu that even the milk of a kosher animal
is a חידוש. chiddush. Why is milk of a kosher animal חידוש?
chiddush? Well first of all right I know kids often ask this
question, why isn't milk פליישיג? fleishig? It comes from a
cow. The whole problem of cooking a king you know meat in
its mother's milk is because it comes from the same animal. Anyway
but that's not the חידוש chiddush why it's not פליישיג. fleishig. The
חידוש chiddush is why is it not אבר מן החי? eiver min
hachai? Right it comes from the animal while it's alive. Now the
best answer to that is the גמרא Gemara says is that it's
not an אבר. eiver. But we also know בשר מן החי basar
min hachai is אסור. assur. But it's not בשר. basar. It's not
an אבר, eiver, it's not בשר, basar, that really is the simple
answer that although it comes from a live animal it falls you
know between the categories. But the גמרא Gemara says no, it's still
a חידוש. chiddush. כיון דחידוש הוא דאמר מר, Keivan de'chiddush hu de'amar
mar, I'm sorry I jumped ahead. I'm always doing that. I jumped
ahead. We're going to get to the אבר מן החי eiver min
hachai in a minute. There's another חידוש chiddush before we get to
that. What? What's the חידוש? chiddush? דאמר מר דם נעכר ונעשה חלב.
de'amar mar dam ne'char vena'aseh chalav.
The גמרא Gemara in נידה Niddah asks why do women not menstruate
while they are nursing? And it has two theories. One is because
the menstrual blood is sort of transfers into milk in order to
nurse the child. So therefore that's why they're not nursing because the
extra blood that normally would be menstrual blood has transformed into milk.
The other explanation is the somewhat more logical one which is just
her body is more physically weak and it didn't talk about hormones.
So anyway it said her body is physically weak and therefore she's
not yet it hasn't recovered yet for her to begin to menstruate
again. Anyway according to the first theory, so milk is transformed blood.
So why are we allowed to drink milk? Why isn't it like
eating blood? So therefore it's a חידוש. chiddush. So since we say
that the blood congeals and turns into
milk, וכיון דחידוש הוא, vekeivan dechiddush hu, since even milk of a
kosher animal is a חידוש, chiddush, בבהמה טמאה נמי לישתרי, bevehemah teme'ah
nami lishteri, maybe it should also be kosher even of a non-kosher
animal because the whole idea that you can eat milk all together
is a חידוש. chiddush. קמשמע לן, kamashma lan, you need a special
verse by milk. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute. הניחא למאן
דאמר דם נעכר ונעשה חלב, hanicha leman de'amar dam ne'char vena'aseh chalav,
that's good if that's how why you say women don't menstruate because
the blood becomes the milk. אלא למאן דאמר איבריה מתפרקין הימנה ela
leman de'amar evareha mitparakin heimena that her limbs are like sort of
you know sort of loose, right, ואינה חוזרת עליה ve'einah chozeret aleha
she doesn't get back her strength עד עשרים וארבעה חודש ad esrim
ve'arba'ah chodesh for 24 months, so it's not because somehow a connection
of blood to milk. So מאי איכא למימר, mai ika lemeimar, so
there's no what's the חידוש chiddush by the fact that we can
drink milk? איצטריך, itztrich, no, there's a חידוש. chiddush. סלקא דעתך אמינא,
salka da'atach amina, here was what I was jumping to, הואיל וליכא
מידי דאתי מחי ושרי, ho'il veleika midi de'ati michay veshari, since there's
nothing normally that comes from a live animal that is permitted, ושרי
רחמנא veshari rachmana that the Torah permits, והאי חלב כי אבר מן
החי הוא, vehai chalav ke'ever min hachay hu, this milk should maybe
be like אבר מן החי. ever min hachay. Notice how the גמרא
Gemara genericizes it. Nothing that comes from a live thing because it
really isn't אבר מן החי, ever min hachay, it's not בשר מן
החי, basar min hachay, but I might have thought let's put it
roughly in the same category and say it's permitted, ושרי, veshari, and
nevertheless it's
permitted. הילכך אפילו בבהמה טמאה לישתרי, hilkach afilu bevehemah teme'ah lishteri, let
it also be permissible in a kosher in a non-kosher animal. קמשמע
לן, kamashma lan, therefore you needed a verse to tell me even
non-kosher. Now if you wanted to reframe it a little bit, first
of all I would have emphasized like I said before that it
doesn't taste at all like the original thing, so it's quite different
than the idea of like fish brine or animal fat you know
juices or whatever. It doesn't taste at all like the thing that
the meat that's טמא. And the other thing you could also say
is what does it mean to be a part of the animal,
a product of the animal, right? So something that maybe is produced
like milk. I mean for example the גמרא's Gemara going to have
to figure out why bee honey is permissible. So what does it
actually mean? So something that actually you know if you were to
basically cut the animal you know right there physically in front of
you this thing is there like the juices are in the meat,
that obviously is part of the animal. But the milk which you
basically you know need to sort of you know squeeze you know
in order to to come out. I mean if you cut open
an udder is there milk sitting in the in the what do
you call it? There is. Yes. Okay. Right because the גמרא Gemara.
talked about that in חולין Chullin about cooking a so alright so
maybe my point is not such a good one because it really
is there in the udder as well. But nevertheless you know you
wonder how much is it something that the animal is producing and
how much is it considered something that is part of the animal.
So the idea before like the juices or whatever that's part of
the animal. Milk is something that's being produced. So anyway that's how
I sort of more would have framed why it's a חידוש. chiddush.
And maybe that's the point of the גמרא. Gemara Why is אבר
מן החי ever min hachay it's not considered אבר מן החי ever
min hachay besides the point I said that it's not a limb
and it's not meat because it's not really part of the animal,
it's produced by the animal but it's not part of the animal.
So therefore I might think that it's not in the category of
things that are part of the animal that are forbidden. So it
says nevertheless it is. At the end result though we get the
very important conclusion that not only are non-kosher animals and the juices
of the meat and whatever forbidden, but even things that are produced
by the non-kosher animals even if they don't taste like the animal
itself, so even things like milk, even that would be forbidden. And
that is the very important principle of יוצא מן הטמא טמא. And
now we're going to have to deal with bee honey which we
will get to. So let's take a look at how the גמרא
Gemara continues. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. וחלב דבהמה טהורה
מנלן דשרי? vechalav debehemah tehorah minalan deshari?
Now that you've said prove now the whole proof rested on the
fact that we that milk was an exception because it was permitted
in a kosher animal. So how did you know whoever told you
that milk was kosher? Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says now obviously
some obvious answers will occur to you so let's take a look.
אילימא מדאסר רחמנא בשר בחלב, eileima mide'asar rachmana basar bechalav,
so the fact that meat and milk is forbidden, so לחודיה שרי
lechudeih shari
implicitly each one separately is permitted. No. ואימא חלב לחודיה אסור, ve'eima
chalav lechudeih asur,
maybe milk itself is forbidden. Again the reason milk would be forbidden
is it would be a type of אבר מן החי. ever min
hachay. Maybe so I would say חלב לחודיה אסור באכילה ומותר בהנאה,
chalav lechudeih asur ba'achilah umutar behana'ah, it would be forbidden to eat
but you could get benefit. ובשר בחלב דהנאה נמי אסור, ubasar bechalav
dehana'ah nami asur,
why does the Torah have to forbid meat and milk? Because maybe
milk was always forbidden, but when you cook them together, it even
becomes more forbidden, forbidden in benefit. Now, ולרבי שמעון דשרי בהנאה, uleRabbi
Shimon desharei behana'ah, how about Reb Shimon? Reb
Shimon says that you're allowed to get benefit from meat and milk,
so according to him, obviously the milk was already permissible. Why else
would you have to say it's forbidden? No, משכחת לה למילקי על
בישולי, meshkachat lah lemilkei al bishulei,
maybe in order to get lashes for cooking. Yes, eating you could
never eat milk maybe, but why did the Torah forbid meat and
milk? In order to prohibit even the act of cooking them together.
אלא, so you can't prove that milk is permissible from the fact
that there's a prohibition of meat and milk. אלא, מדגלי רחמנא דפסולי
מוקדשים, midegali rachmana depisulei mukdashim,
since the Torah tells you that by animals that used to be
sacrifices and were redeemed, what does it say? תזבח, tizbach, it says
you can slaughter them and we say the דרשה drasha is ולא
גיזה, velo giza, no shears them, בשר, bassar, you can eat the
meat, ולא חלב, velo chalav, you can't eat the milk. So since
we have an established דרשה drasha that you can't take milk a
animal that was a redeemed sacrifice, that suggests דחולין, dechullin, a normal
non-sacrificial animal, שרי, sharei, you could get the milk. I said maybe
not. ואימא דחולין באכילה אסור ובהנאה שרי, ve'eima dechullin ba'achila assur ubehana'ah
sharei, same point. Maybe a non-sacrifice, you can't eat the milk but
you can get benefit. דקדשים, dekodashim, something that was once a sacrifice,
בהנאה נמי אסור behana'ah nami assur is also forbidden in benefit. So
although we are you cannot infer that milk is permissible because it's
forbidden, a special case is forbidden, maybe that special case makes it
forbidden in benefit, but maybe milk as a standard rule is forbidden
to eat. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא, מדכתיב, ella midechtiv, so
we'll learn it out, here you go Charlie because I know you
love when we learn out from נ"ך, Nach, so we learn from
a פסוק pasuk in משלי Mishlei that says ודי חלב עזים ללחמך,
vedei chalav izim lelachmecha, sufficient milk of the goats for your bread,
ללחם ביתך, lelechem beitecha, for the bread of your house, the food
of your house, וחיים לנערותיך, vechayim lena'arotecha, and life for your young
daughters. So ודי, vedei, so you see you're eating milk. No, ודילמא
לסחורה, vedilma leschora, maybe it means you milk your cows, you sell
the milk to non-Jews, and you use the proceeds to feed your
family, but not that they're eating the family they're eating the milk
directly. What? Hasn't Charlie told us that people didn't use to drink
milk until very recently? No, I didn't say. No, I told you
they made cheese out of it.
I told you that, that's why in חולין Chullin it always talks
about
eating putting cheese and meat at the same
time and never
milk because you would never actually drink milk, but yes, you would
still sell it for making into cheese. Michael, you're going to I'm
sure you're going to quote a פסוק that the גמרא's Gemara going
to get up to, so let's wait. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this, אלא מדכתיב, midechtiv, ואת עשרת חריצי החלב, ve'et
asseret charitzei hachalav, the ten חריצי charitzei of milk, which here means
which here basically means cheese, okay, I'm not exactly sure how חריץ
charitz means cheese, but anyway exactly the point that they didn't eat
milk, but these are basically like things that are made to congeal
milk, things made into cheese. Cheese, cheese. Okay, there you go. So
anyway, this was what this was what דוד David was supposed to
bring his brothers in the battlefield, remember when he was sent by
his father ישי? Yishai? So you see they're eating they're eating cheese.
ודילמא לסחורה, vedilma leschora, maybe he's supposed to sell them and use
the money to buy bread for them. So the גמרא says אטו
דרכא דשמא למכור לסחורה, atu darcha deshamma limkor leschora, what, you're bringing
it out to them in a war, you have time to go
ahead and sell it? ואיבעית אימא מהכא, ve'iba'it eima mehacha, or from
here, ארץ זבת חלב ודבש, eretz zavat chalav udevash, a land flowing
of milk and honey. ואי לא דשרי, ve'i lo desharei, and if
it were not permissible to eat the milk, משתבח לן קרא במידי
דלא חזי, mishtabach lan kra bemidi dela chazi, would the Torah praise
the land of Israel with something that wasn't fit? ואיבעית אימא, ve'iba'it
eima, if you want you could say to eat מהכא, mehacha, לכו
שברו ואכלו, lechu shivru ve'ocholu, go sell and eat, ולכו שברו, ulechu
shivru, go purchase or go purchase and eat I should say, go
purchase בלא כסף ובלא מחיר, belo chesef uvelo mechir, without money and
without exchange, יין וחלב, yayin vechalav, go purchase wine and milk, and
the previous verse said and eat. Okay, so therefore you see that
you're allowed to eat milk. Since you're allowed to eat milk, that's
a חידוש chiddush because I might have thought that milk was I
don't know a type of blood or I would have thought milk
was a type of אבר מן החי. ever min hachai. Once you
see that milk is permissible, maybe it's even permissible of non-kosher animals.
And again, the way I would frame that is, it's not just
a part of a non-kosher animal, it's a product of a non-kosher
animal, and therefore it's less a part of it, it doesn't even
taste like it. And therefore we learn out from either את הגמל
et hagamal or גמל גמל, this very important principle which ties us
back to the משנה, that היוצא מן הטמא טמא, hayotzei min hatamei
tamei, that even products of non-kosher animals are not kosher, and we
will continue with this tomorrow.